<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on glenn ryan</title>
    <link>http://glennryan.info/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on glenn ryan</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; Glenn Ryan 2016. All rights reserved.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 27 Feb 2016 14:08:44 -0800</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://glennryan.info/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>a clean slate: deleting all tweets with python</title>
      <link>http://glennryan.info/2016/02/27/a-clean-slate-deleting-all-tweets-with-python</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 27 Feb 2016 14:08:44 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://glennryan.info/2016/02/27/a-clean-slate-deleting-all-tweets-with-python</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As my first order of business, I was looking to to delete all prior tweets from my account, since I plan to start using Twitter in a more professional capacity from now on. To do so, I see there are &lt;a href=&#34;tweetdelete.net&#34;&gt;various sites&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.gocardigan.com/&#34;&gt;services&lt;/a&gt; out there to assist with that. But part of beginning this blog was a commitment to exploring how I can use official  APIs, third-party libraries or my own code from scratch to accomplish things on the web.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I found this nice Python script, courtesy of &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/davej&#34;&gt;Dave Jeffery&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script src=&#34;https://gist.github.com/davej/113241.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I registered my twitter application under bird_eater (ha, get it? because it&amp;rsquo;s Python getting rid of tweets&amp;hellip; eh) and put in my key and secret. I then followed the directions from the script&amp;rsquo;s output et voilà! I am now tweet-free. I can restart my Twitter profile with a clean slate &amp;mdash; notwithstanding the other parts of my account.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, why not take care of those things, too? To take this further, I should expand on this script to make it a bit more sophisticated. Some ideas could be deleting certain tweets, unfollowing accounts, removing likes and lists, etc. That could be a promising project.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>